Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Caricatures and Cartoons 1643, 1756-1943, 1977 PR 10
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Antebellum Period, 1841-1859
  - Rough & Ready Presidential Cabinet in 1849. [President Zachary Taylor] (Folder FF-66, Item 1849-10)
  - Californians in Jamaica. A Good Freight. No. 1. [Gold Rush], 1849 (Folder FF-67, Item 1849-11)
    Lithograph: signed A. Duperly.
  - Californians Type. The Pilot Fish and the Shark. No. 2. [Gold Rush], 1849 (Folder FF-67, Item 1849-12)
    Lithograph: Lith. by A. Duperly, Kingston Jamaica.
  - One of the Codfish Aristocracy [Astor House Riot], 1849 (Folder FF-67, Item 1849-13)
    Lithograph: Nagel & Weingartner Print. Published by Elton, New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: March 31, 1906.
  - From the Place We Hear About. [Gold Rush], 1849 (Folder FF-67, Item 1849-14)
    Lithograph: Lith. & published by Serrell & Perkins, New York. Although 1849-14 and 1849-15 have very similar titles, the images are different.
  - The Place We Hear About. [Gold Rush], 1849 (Folder FF-67, Item 1849-15)
    Lithograph: Lith. & published by Serrell & Perkins, New York. Although 1849-14 and 1849-15 have very similar titles, the images are different. Acquisition(?) date on front: May 5, 1900.
  - [Two pictures each captioned] Going to California via Fremont's Route! Returning from California via Cape Horn! [Gold Rush], 1849 (Folder FF-67, Item 1849-16)
    Lithograph: Elton Publisher. Acquisition(?) date on front: May 5, 1900.
  - Grand Patent India-Rubber Air Line Railway to California. Competition Defied. [Gold Rush], 1849 (Folder FF-67, Item 1849-17)
  - Fariboles. Jeunes fideles de la Paroisse Notre Dame de Lorette partant en pelerinage pour la Californie. [California Migration, Gold Rush], 1849 (Folder FF-67, Item 1849-19)
    Colored lithograph: Imp. de MeVe Aubert, Paris. "Lorette" was equivalent to "street-walker". Acquisition(?) date on back: June 15, 1957.
  - Mr. Golightly. Bound for California. [Gold Rush], 1849 (Folder FF-67, Item 1849-20)
    Colored lithograph: Published by A. Donelly, New York.
  - Mose, Lize, & Little Mose Going to California. [Gold Rush], 1849 (Folder FF-67, Item 1849-21)
    Colored lithograph: Signed J.L. Magee (pencil); lith. & published J.L. Magee, New York. (Formerly was numbered by N-YHS as 1851-1.)
  - Where's My Thunder? [Webster & Clay, Fugitive Slave Act], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-1)
  - The Sad Parting Between Two Old Friends. [Benton & Foote], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-2)
  - Doing in the Jerseys [New Jersey Railroad], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-4)
    Lithograph: published for the people of New Jersey by Serrell & Perkins, New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: March 31, 1906.
  - The Second Deluge. First Appearance of Jenny Lind in America. [Social], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-5)
    Lithograph: Published by W. Schaus, New York. Jenny Lind was known as the "Swedish Nightingale". P.T. Barnum convinced her to tour in America in 1850.
  - Practical Illustration of the Fugitive Slave Law. [Slavery], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-6)
    Lithograph: Signed E.C. Del.
  - Some Pumpkins. Trotting his mile in 2:10. beating "Lightning" by nearly 5 lengths, on a descending grade; and carrying 25 lbs over weight., 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-7)
  - [Under right hand image] Upper Ten Dom, Entering Washington Square... [Left hand image] Upper Ten Dom, Leaving the "Square". [Social], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-10)
    Lithograph: Published by Gobble, Viper & Co., published simultaneously in London, Paris & New York. Acquisition info on back: Purchase, July 15, 1949, Wilbur Fund
  - Conquering Prejudice to Save the Union. [Fugitive Slave Act], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-11)
    Lithograph: Anonymous. Acquisition date on front: Apr. 16, 1914.
  - Illustration of Jenny Lind's Mocking-Bird Song. Papageno, Prince of Iranistan in Mozart's celebrated Opera "The Magic Flute". Pl. 5. [Social], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item c.1850-12a)
    Lithograph: Signed W.A. (monogram).
  - Parody as not quite of Norma. Pl. 6. Piano carissima! Don't Frighten the Subscribers! [Social], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item c.1850-12b)
  - Massachusetts Baby Show. [Political Candidates], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-13)
    Lithograph: J. Curtis Lith. N. York. The "babies" are identified in brown ink.
  - The Resurrection of Henry Box Brown at Philadelphia, Who Escaped from Richmond Va. in a box 3 feet long 21/2 ft deep and 2 ft wide. [Slavery], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-14)
    Lithograph: anonymous. Acquisition(?) date on front: April 9, 1901.
  - Effects of the Fugitive-Slave-Law. [To the left, quote from the Bible ... To the right, quote from the Declaration of Independence ...] [Slavery], 1850 (Folder FF-68, Item 1850-15)
    Lithograph: Published by Huff & Bloede, New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: July 2(?), 19/06.
  - Hum-Bug [P.T. Barnum], 1851 (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-2)
    Lithograph: Lith. in color by L. Rosenthal, Philadelphia. (From "A Comic Natural History"). Acquisition(?) date on front: Dec. 31, 1903.
  - Old Shad & Young, 1851 (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-3)
    Lithograph of Rosenthal, Philadelphia. (From "A Commic Natural History").
  - The Game-Cock & The Goose [Winfield Scott, Franklin Pierce], circa 1851 (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-4)
    Lithograph: Signed J.L. Magee dell[sic]. Pub. at T.W. Strong Lith., New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: April 16, 1914.
  - [Left hand image] The Gladiatos [Gladiators] of the Senate! The Pious Dodge! Coward! Liar! [Right hand image] The Bulleys of the House. They work very hard and only get $8 a day and their Mileage., 1851 (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-5)
    Images contrast a Senate fight, in which the combatants dodge each other's weaponry, with a House of Representatives fight, which is fisticuffs.
  - Two of the Fe'He Males [Feminist Movement], 1851 (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-6)
  - The Great Bloomer Prize Fight for the Champions Belt. [Feminist Movement, Tom Hyer], 1851 (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-7)
    Lithograph: Entered ... 1851 by J.L. Magee. Acquisition(?) date on front: May 15, 1906.
  - What's Sauce for the Goose Is Sauce for the Gander. [Two images labeled North and South respectively.] [Fugitive Slave Act], 1851 (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-8)
    Lithograph: Signed E.W.C. (E.W. Clay); Pub. at 152 Nassau Street ... Entered ... 1851 by E.W. Clay.
  - Above: Life in San Francisco. [Cut] Below: The King's Campaign or Removal of the Deposites. Composed and sung by Frank Ball [50 lines of verse beneath], 1851 (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-9)
  - Above: Pl. 11. That Hat Again! the real cause of the Eclipse, July 28th 1851. Below: Deacon, seeing the Archbishop [John Hughes] in trouble ... (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-10)
    Lithograph: Signed AW (monogram). Image also refers to New York merchant Mr. Genin.
  - The Happy Family Exhibited since 1776 in Uncle Sam's Republican Gardens for the Instruction of Nations! [Concerns U.S. Involvement in Cuba], 1851 (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-11)
    Lithograph by Nagel and Weingaertner, after design by Adam Weingaertner, New York. Acquisition(?) date on back: Purchase 1981.
  - In Full Bloom!, 1851 (Folder FF-69, Item 1851-12)
    Appears to be folded card: by Beck & Co., London. Dated on the card: 10 Nov. 1851. On the inside of the card, stamped twice "BCL" [Bella Landauer]
  - Political Hypocrisy. Disappointed Candidates Congratulating Genl. Frank Pierce on his Nomination for the Presidency. [Democratic Party Presidential Candidates], 1852 (Folder FF-70, Item 1852-1)
    Lithograph: Signed E.W.C. (E.W. Clay); published by J. Childs, New York.
  - Capability and Availability. [Presidential Election], 1852 (Folder FF-70, Item 1852-2)
  - A Bad Egg. Fuss and Feathers. [Winfield Scott], 1852 (Folder FF-70, Item 1852-3)
    Lithograph: Entered ... 1852 by P. Smith ... (New York).
  - [Left hand image] Scene in a New Hampshire Court - General Pierce Examining a Witness. [Right hand image] Scene in a New Hampshire Village - General Pierce The Good Samaritan. [Franklin Pierce], 1852 (Folder FF-70, Item 1852-4)
    Lithograph: Published by T.W. Strong, New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: April 16, 1914.
  - Fighting and Fainting. "That Pierce-ing Cry - He Faints on the Battle Field." [Franklin Pierce], 1852 (Folder FF-70, Item 1852-5)
    Lithograph: Strong Lith., New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: April 16, 1914.
  - Soliciting a Vote. [Presidential Election: Webster, Houston, Douglas, Scott], 1852 (Folder FF-70, Item 1852-6)
    2 copies. Lithograph: No imprint. On one copy, written on back (pencil), "Gift of Miss Anne K. Hays Apr. 27, 1936".
  - House Hunting!! Bloomer Ladies Looking for a House for the Next Term. [Presidential Election], 1852 (Folder FF-71, Item 1852-7)
    Lithograph: No imprint. Acquisition(?) date on front: March 2, 1905.
  - The Champion of Despotism. [J.W. Webb, Lajos Kossuth], 1852 (Folder FF-71, Item 1852-8)
    Lithograph: No imprint. Acquisition(?) date on front: Dec. 9/99.
  - Loco Foco Hunters Treeing a Candidate [Pierce], 1852 (Folder FF-71, Item 1852-9)
    Lithograph: Signed H.O.
  - No Go and Going with A Rush. [Presidential Election], 1852 (Folder FF-71, Item 1852-10)
    Lithograph: Signed EWC (monogram, E.W. Clay); published by J. Childs, New York.
  - Save Him From His Friends _ Loco Foco Ingratitude, Burial of the Old Fogies. [Presidential Election, Democratic Party], 1852 (Folder FF-71, Item 1852-11)
    Lithograph: T.W. Strong, Lith., New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 16, 1914.
  - Ornithology. Two Great Birds of the United States, not described by Audubon. [Scott & Pierce, Mason-Dixon Line], 1852 (Folder FF-71, Item 1852-12)
    Lithograph: Signed EWC (monogram, E.W. Clay).
  - Position of the Democratic Party in 1852. "Freemen of America, how long will you be led by such leaders!" [Slavery] (Folder FF-71, Item 1852-13)
    Lithograph: Sold by Bela Marsh, Boston, MA. Entered ... 1852 by William K. Leach ... Acquisition(?) date on front: April 16, 1914.
  - Great Foot-Race for the Presidential Purse ($100,000 and Pickings) Over the Union Course 1852. [Presidential Election] (Folder FF-71, Item 1852-14)
    Lithograph: For sale at 2 Spruce Street (N. Currier's address).
  - A Grand Slave Hunt, Or Trial of Speed for the Presidency, between the Celebrated Nags Black Dan, Lewis Cass, and Haynau. [Fugitive Slave Act, Slavery], 1852 (Folder FF-71, Item 1852-15)
    Lithograph: Signed T.C. del N.Y. Acquisition(?) date on front: Jan. 12, 1914.
  - Pap, Soup, And Chowder. [Presidential Election], 1852 (Folder FF-71, Item 1852-16)
    Lithograph: Signed J.L. Magee, del., Entered ... 1852 by P. Smith ...
  - A Contested Seat [Presidential Election], 1852 (Folder FF-72, Item 1852-17)
  - Harmony in the Wigwam! Democracy of the Right Brand-y. [Presidential Election], 1852 (Folder FF-72, Item 1852-18)
  - April Fools! [Presidential Election], 1852 (Folder FF-72, Item 1852-19)
    Lithograph: No imprint. This cartoon and 6 others, though encountered separately in collections, appeared in the number dated April 1, 1852, of the Old Soldier, published at 69 Nassau Street, New York.
  - Grand Fight for the Champions Belt between Granite Pierce and Old Chapultepec. [Presidential Election], 1852 (Folder FF-72, Item 1852-20)
    Lithograph: Signed J.L. Magee, published by P. Smith, New York.
  - Whig Candidates for the Presidency. [Van Buren, Scott, Seward, Fillmore, Webster], 1852 (Folder FF-72, Item 1852-21)
    Lithograph: Published by J. Childs, New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: June 2, 1908.
  - Managing a Candidate. [Presidential Election], 1852 (Folder FF-72, Item 1852-22)
    Lithograph: Entered ... 1852 by P. Smith ...
  - Young America. [Democratic Party under Pierce], 1852 (Folder FF-72, Item 1852-23)
    Wash Drawing.
  - Gas and Glory (Two pictures are titled "New Hampshire" and "Mexico".) [Franklin Pierce, Presidential Election], 1852 (Folder FF-72, Item 1852-24)
  - "The Blind Man's Bluff," or The President's Election for 1852. Chorus dancing and singing Yankee Doodle. Pl. 9. (Folder FF-72, Item 1852-25)
    Lithograph: Signed After [Robert D.] Wilkie and WA (monogram).
  - A Paid Fire Department, As It Is Likely To Be Under The Contract System, 1853 (Folder FF-73, Item 1853-1)
    Lithograph: J.L. Magee, Publisher, Philadelphia. Acquisition(?) date on front: Dec. 6, 1906.
  - A "Circulating Medium" secured by "Public Stocks." [Wild Cat Banker], 1853 (Folder FF-73, Item 1853-2)
    Lithograph: Lith. & published by N. Currier, New York. Acquisition(?) date on back: Feb. 26 1900.
  - Paid Fire Department., 1853 (Folder FF-73, Item 1853-3)
    Lithograph: Signed by P. Kramer (in reverse); published by P.E. Abel, Philadelphia.
  - The "Ostend Doctrine." [Use of force to seize Cuba for national security], 1854 (Folder FF-73, Item 1854-1(Copy 1))
    Lithograph: [By Louis Maurer] [Currier & Ives]. Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 12, 1906.
  - A Good Tree Cannot Bring Forth Evil Fruit: Neither Can a Corrupt Tree Bring Forth Good Fruit. Matt. VII 18. [Anti-Slavery], 1854 (Folder FF-73, Item 1854-2)
  - Above: Sunday Travel, No. I. Below: An "Old Hoss" and the "Mare." [Mayor Harvey - Phila], 1854 (Folder FF-73, Item 1854-3)
    Lithograph: No imprint. Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 16, 1914.
  - "Outward Bound, The Quay of Dublin." [Irish Immigration], 1854 (Folder FF-73, Item 1854-4)
    Colored lithograph: Painted by T. Nicol. Drawn on stone by T.H. Maguire lithographic artist to the Queen. Printed by M & N Hanhart. Published by Henry Graves & Co., London, and Williams, Stevens and Williams, New York. Acquisition(?) date on back: March 25, 1959 (Abbott & Lenox).
  - "Homeward Bound, The Quay of New York." [Irish Immigration], 1854 (Folder FF-73, Item 1854-5)
  - "No Higher Law" [Fugitive Slave Act], 1854 (Folder FF-73, Item 1854-6)
    Woodcut: For sale by Wm. Harned, New York.
  - Uncle Sam's Youngest Son: Citizen Know-Nothing, 1854 (Folder FF-146, Item 1854-7)
    Bust portrait of man in oval. Lithograph by Sarony & Co. Published by Williams, Stevens, Williams & Co. 2 copies: one stamped "Victor Wilbour".; the second copy is a variant, tinted, acquisition(?) date on front: April 30, 1915 (Stevens collection)
  - Virtuous Indignation of John Bull at the Horrors of the War for the Union. [Benjamin Butler Order 28, New Orleans], 1854, 1862 (Folder FF-73, Item 1854-8)
    Wood Engraving: Signed Mullen. On back is a second copy of The Ostend Doctrine (1854-1).
  - A Grave Subject for the New Yorkers [Street Cleaning], 1854 (Folder FF-73, Item 1854-9)
    Lithograph: Designed, lith. & published by Hatch & Severin, New York.
  - A Brush on the Road. Mile Heats, Best Two in Three. [Social], 1855 (Folder FF-73, Item 1855-1)
    Lithograph: Signed T. Worth, lith. & published by N. Currier, New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: March 1900. Stamped on back: "F. Nordstrom. Collection No. ..."
  - Liberty, The Fair Maid of Kansas _ In the Hands of the "Border Ruffians". [Bleeding Kansas: Marcy, Pierce, Buchanan, Cass, Douglas], 1855 (Folder FF-73, Item 1855-2 (Copy 1))
  - The Fisherman Astray! [Church Property Bill], 1855 (Folder FF-73, Item 1855-3)
    Line engraving and etching: Copyright secured by G. Daelly. Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 6, 1906.
  - The Discord. [Battle of the Sexes], 1855 (Folder FF-73, Item 1855-4)
    Colored lithograph: Pubished and for sale by Valentine Lutz, New York. Lith. by F. Heppenheimer, New York. On back, lithograph portrait of Henriette Sonntag: lith: Plann del. Charles Schuler so. Published by Stich, Druck u. Verlag von C. Kneller in Stuttgart. Also stamped: "F. Nordstrom. Collection No. ..."
  - Disturbed by the Night Mare., 1855 (Folder FF-73, Item 1855-5)
    Colored lithograph: published by Kellogg & Comstock, New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 5 1900.
  - The True Holy Alliance [Anti-Catholicism, Popery], circa 1855 (Folder FF-73, Item 1855-No #)
    Copyright by G. Daelly.
  - "Young '76" [Boy in Soldier's Garb], 1855 (Folder FF-146, Item 1855-No #)
    Lith by Lafosse. Painted by C.G. Corbin. Published by W. Schaus. Imp. Fois. Delarue, Paris.
  - Forcing Slavery Down the Throat of a Freesoiler. [Bleeding Kansas, Douglas, Pierce, Buchanan, Cass], 1856 (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-1)
    Lithograph: Published by J.L. Magee, Philadelphia. Acquisition(?) date on front: April 16, 1914.
  - The Morning after the Election - November 1856. [Presidential Election, Buchanan, Fillmore] (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-2)
    Lithograph: Published by Childs, Philadelphia.
  - The Presidential Campaign of '56 [Slavery, Kansas], 1856 (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-3)
    Lithograph: Published by John Fahnestock, Cincinati(?). Graphic includes the use of term "Peculiar Institution" ny Buchanan
  - Southern Chivalry - Argument against Club's. [Kansas, Slavery, Preston Brooks, Charles Sumner], 1856 (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-4)
    Lithograph: Signed J.L. Magee, del.
  - A Serviceable Garment - or Reverie of a Bachelor. [Ostend Manifesto, Buchanan, Cuba, Slavery], 1856 (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-5)
    Lithograph: [Louis Maurer] [Currier & Ives]. Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 2, 19/06.
  - The Democratic Platform. [Buchanan, Pierce, etc., Slavery], 1856 (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-6)
    Lithograph: [Currier & Ives]. Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 2/06.
  - The Balls are Rolling - Clear the Track [Presidential Election, Free Soil, Fremont], 1856 (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-7)
    Lithograph: [Currier & Ives].
  - The Great Presidential Sweepstakes of 1856. Free for all ages, "go as they please" [Presidential Election] (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-8)
    Lithograph: [Currier & Ives]
  - Shall I Vote for Ten Cents a Day? [Presidential Election, Buchanan, Fillmore], 1856 (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-9)
    Lithograph: Published by I. Childs, Philadelphia.
  - The Right Man for the Right Place. [Presidential Election, Slavery], 1856 (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-10)
    Lithograph: [Currier & Ives]. Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr.2, 19/06.
  - The "Mustang" Team [Horace Greeley and other Press, Presidential Election, Fremont], 1856 (Folder FF-74, Item 1856-11)
    Lithograph: [Currier & Ives]. Acquisition(?) date on back: June 3, 19/03.
  - "Buck" Taking the "Pot". [Presidential Election], 1856 (Folder FF-75, Item 1856-12)
    Lithograph: [Currier & Ives]. Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 2, 1906.
  - The Great Republican Reform Party. Calling on Their Candidate. [Presidential Election, Fremont], 1856 (Folder FF-75, Item 1856-13)
    2 copies. Lithograph: [Louis Maurer] [Currier & Ives]. Copy 1: Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 12, 1906.
  - Col. Fremont's Last Grand Exploring Expedition in 1856. [Presidential Election, Fremont, Beecher, Greeley, Seward] (Folder FF-75, Item 1856-14)
    Lithograph: [Currier & Ives]. Acquisition(?) date on front: Apr. 12, 1906.
  - The Great American Buck Hunt of 1856. [Presidential Election] (Folder FF-75, Item 1856-15)
  - Road to a Know-Nothing Lodge. [American Party, Irish Emigration from America], 1856 (Folder FF-75, Item 1856-16)
    Lithograph: No imprint. Acquisition(?) date on front: Feb. 26, 1900.
  - A Pro Slavery Incantation Scene. or Shakespeare Improved. See MacBeth [Free Soil, Slavery, Fremont], 1856 (Folder FF-75, Item 1856-17)
    Lithograph: No imprint. Stamped on back, "The Gift of Henry O. Havermeyer, Yale 1900. Collection of United States Naval Prints and Painting"
  - [Below upper image]: Dream of a Black Republican. Before 4th of November 1856. [Below lower image]: The Fourth of November 1856. [Presidential Election] (Folder FF-75, Item 1856-18)
    Lithograph: Entered ... 1856 by Edw. De Gotzkow(?) and Joe De Kammerhuber ... Acquisition(?) date on front: March 26, 1901 (1907?).
  - Turkey, John Bull & Monsieur Frog-Eater in a Bad Fix. [Crimean War], 1856 (Folder FF-75, Item 1856-19)
  - [Above image]: The Right Man in the Right Place [in a Stock]. [Below image]: "Bully Brooks" [Preston S. Brooks], 1856 (Folder FF-75, Item 1856-20 (Copy 1))
    Lithograph: No imprint. Acquisition(?) date on back: Jan 12, 1914.
  - Queen of the Amazons Attacked by a Lion. [Gen. Nath. Lyon], 1856 (Folder FF-75, Item 1856-21)
    Lithograph: Lith. & published by N. Currier.
  - Fancied Security, or the Rats on a Bender [Millard Fillmore], 1856 (Folder FF-68, Item 1856-22)
    Lithograph attributed to Currier & Ives in Gale Research's catalogue raisonné. For sale at No. 2 Spruce Street (N. Currier's address). Acquisition date on front: Apr. 12, 1906. (Formerly coded by N-YHS as 1850-3.)
  - Stump Speaking, 1856 (Folder FF-155, Item 1856-No #)
    Engraved by Gautier. Print from the painting by George C. Bingham. Published by Groupel & Co.
  - Mormon Breastworks and U.S. Troops. Officer U.S.A.: "Trumpeter! Sound the retreat! We never can carry that battery in the World, Cesar himself would be defeated before such breastworks.", 1857 (Folder FF-76, Item 1857-1)
    Image depicts armed Mormon men using women and children as human shields against troops.
  - Suspending Specie Payments, 1857 (Folder FF-76, Item 1857-2)
    2 copies. Lithograph: For sale at 217 Walnut Street. Phila. Copy 2 (colored): stamped on back, "The Gift of Henry O. Havemeyer, Yale 1900. Collection of United States Naval Prints and Painting." Acquisition(?) date on back of copy 2: Oct. 7, 1946.
  - The Great Pictorial Romance of the Age, or Steam Ship Commodores & United States Mail Contractors. [Transportation/Mail], 1857 (Folder FF-76, Item 1857-3)
    Lithograph: Colored. Published by Chas. F. Gildersleave (New York). Acquisition(?) date on back: December 14, 1977, Old Print Gallery, Washington, DC.
  - The Little Giant-In The Character of the Gladiator. [Douglas & Buchanan], 1858 (Folder FF-76, Item 1958-1)
    Lithograph: For sale at 217 Walnut St. Phila. Stamped on back, "The Gift of Henry O. Havemeyer, Yale 1900. Collection of United States Naval Prints and Painting." Also, Acquisition(?) date on back: Oct. 7, 1946.
  - Panic Season. Good Times for Non-Speculators. 1858. [Social] (Folder FF-76, Item 1858-2)
    Lithograph: Published by Charles Magnus & Co., New York. Acquisition(?) date on front: Sept. 27, 1901(?)
  - Aunty Lecompton settling with Richard. [Philadelphia Election, May 1858] (Folder FF-76, Item 1858-3)
    Lithograph: No imprint. Handbill size. Acquisition(?) date on back: Feb. 12, 1905.
  - Pl. 3. The New-York Elephant. National Monument to be erected at the top of New City-Hall. [Fernando Wood, New York City Politics], 1859 (Folder FF-76, Item 1859-1)
    Lithgraph: Signed WA.
- Series V. Civil War and Post-War Period, 1860-1868
  The series includes prints ranging from 1860 to 1868, that is, from the election of Abraham Lincoln through the Civil War and concluding with the election of Ulysses S. Grant in 1868. There are about 280 prints in the series.
  Prints from 1860 include all the candidates in a 4-way race: Lincoln of Illinois and Hannibal Hamlin of Maine (Republican), John C. Breckinridge of Kentucky and Joseph Lane of Oregon (Southern Democratic), John Bell of Tennessee and Edward Everett of Massachusetts (Constitutional Union), and Stephen A. Douglas of Illinois and Herschel V. Johnson of Georgia (Northern Democratic). Horace Greeley of the Tribune appears often in the campaign caricatures (in support of Lincoln), as do other depictions of the press. The image of Lincoln as the "rail splitter" is frequently used as a metaphor for him splitting the Union, with the abolition of slavery as a principal theme of the election.